Lucas Barros

Metro Vancouver, BC | V3T 0N2 | (604) 790-1323 | LucasCavalcanteDeBarros@gmail.com <u>linkedin.com/in/lucascbarros</u> | <u>github.com/LucasCBarros</u>

SUMMARY:

Praised iOS Developer with over five years experience, skilled in object-oriented design, programming, and debugging. I actively engage in the entire app development process, from project initiation to feature integration, testing, troubleshooting, and submission to the App Store. My proficiency in agile methodologies facilitates smooth cooperation with product managers and designers, translating requirements and mockups into outstanding user experiences.

KEY SKILLS

- ▶ TvOS, WatchOS, iOS Development with Swift & XCode
- ► Architectures: MVC, MVP, MVVM and VIPER
- ► Frameworks: Foundation, UIKit, SwiftUI Basics, CoreData, Push Notifications, and more
- ▶ **Testing:** Unit testing with XCTest
- ► CocoaPods, Swift Package Manager
- ▶ Strong debugging and problem-solving skills
- ► Network communications with RESTful APIs using URLSession (Debugging with Charles Proxy)

- ► CI/CD and AppStore submission
- ▶ Firebase Analytics, Crashlitics and Database
- ▶ Strong UI/UX skills and attention to details
- ▶ Jira, Confluence, Bitrise, Azure, Figma, Zeplin
- ▶ Code Review, Pair Programming & Clean Code
- ► SQL & NoSQL databases
- ▶ Design Patterns & Code Documentation
- Version control (GitHub, Bitbucket, SourceTree)
- ▶ Scrum Developer Certification

WORK EXPERIENCE

iOS TEAM LEADER at Compass Digital / ON, Canada

Jun 2022 - Nov 2023

iOS Team Leader (Feb 2023 - Nov 2023)

- > Proposed, implemented & documented a GitFlow to standardize the way we deployed Feature work and Hot-fixes.
- > Conducted team meetings to discuss releases, improvements, standards and strategies. Then documented the agreements.
- > Was a point of contact for the iOS team so the BE, Design and Product could get technical insights without disrupting development.
- ➤ Worked close to Scrum Master making suggestions to improve our team's way of working. Partnered with the DevOps team to manage our on-call rotation & follow up on incident management. Participated in the hiring process to fill a senior position.

iOS Developer (Jun 2022 - Jan 2023)

- ➤ Developed Boost, Thrive and J&J Kitchen and maintained Bitrise & Firebase (Remote-Config, Distribution & Crashlytics).
- ➤ Investigated, mitigated & deployed fixes for urgent Production Issues.
- ➤ Manually released in *AppStore* coordinating with the Product team and managing *Feature Flags*.
- ➤ Developed the rebranding of *Thrive*, standardized the color schemes, button styles and strings improving UX resulting in AppStore evaluation going from 3.2 to 4.2.
- > Collaborated in cross-functional teams including backend, design and product managers to define, design and ship features
- ➤ Reviewed Pull Requests to assert code quality and participated in visual QA avoiding layout issues.
- Worked in On-Call rotation providing prompt solutions to critical issues and releasing fixes within 48h depending on severity.
- ➤ Refactored code such as StoryBoards into auto layout, migrated from *MVP* to *VIPER* while applying the new code standards.
- ➤ Refactored code to enhance code reusability, efficiency and readability, while enforcing Swift style and conventions.

iOS DEVELOPER at AB-Inbev/ Blumenau - SC, Brazil

Nov 2020 - Apr 2022

- ➤ Worked in the BEES app module that enabled clients to open support tickets or contact support center via phone or whatsapp.
- ➤ Developed using **Swift**, **MVVM** architecture with modular components, refactored legacy Objective C code and practiced clean code while **pair programming**. Relied heavily on Azure for CI/CD and **SCM** with **Git**, and Scrum methodology with Jira. Learned from great professionals from our partners CI&T and ThoughtWorks.

iOS DEVELOPER SPECIALIZATION at Apple Developer Academy / Campinas - SP, Brazil

Mar 2017 - Dec 2018

- ➤ 2017: App development basics with Swift also covering Design and Business strategies.
- ➤ **2018:** Developed EasyBoard for *iOS*, *tvOS* & *watchOS* to assist learning processes. Students could post their questions in the AppleTv so teachers and other students can help. Later Apple Developer Academy Detroit asked permission to use it too.

EDUCATION

PROJECTS

Boost, Thrive and J&J Kitchen at Compass Digital

Jun 2022 - Nov 2023

➤ With **Boost** mobile ordering, you can conveniently pre-order meals on campus, facilitating payment through credit/debit cards or your meal plans. While **Thrive** and **J&J Kitchen** aim to provide a personalized and seamless experience with every order, ensuring a delightful dining experience at the office, making payments and scheduling pickup times well in advance.

BEES at AB-Inbev Nov 2020 - Apr 2022

AB-Inbev B2B e-commerce and marketplace platform, where I focused on the customer support module for Latin America, United States and South Africa (while growing and expanding worldwide). Our module is responsible for the solution that guarantees that our clients can open support tickets or contact the support center via phone or whatsapp.

EasyBoard at Apple Developer Academy

Feb 2018 - Dec 2018

➤ The application evolved into an internal tool for the Apple Developer Academy at Eldorado, enhancing flexibility and agility within the learning process. Additionally, we showcased the project at the Mobile Campus hackathon, competing for "best learning solution". Later, the Apple Developer Academy in Detroit sought permission to incorporate it too.

UBorrow at Apple Developer Academy

Dec 2017 - Jan 2018

➤ The app helps those who borrow things like books but seem to forget to whom or when should the person return it. The uses a seamless ui where the item's border gradually turns from green to red as the due date comes closer, that way you can intuitively keep track without having to constantly check the dates. This feature is reinforced with notifications and light and dark themes for the app.

Mindala at Apple Developer Academy

Jul 2017 - Set 2018

➤ The purpose was to increase the users productivity by assisting them to achieve better focus on the tasks by rewarding them with an unique & incredible randomly generated mandala, based on the amount of time they maintained they focus without checking the phone.

SKILL DEVELOPMENT

iOS Development: Architecture [2h] at LinkedIn Learning

Swift: Delegations and Data Sources [1h] at LinkedIn Learning

Swift 5 Essential Training [4h] at LinkedIn Learning

Jan 2022

Movile Next: iOS Specialization [32h] at Movile Group

Certified Scrum Developer training [32h] at Adaptworks in partnership with Eldorado Institute

Nov 2015

VOLUNTEER WORK

STAFF PROSPECTING PARTNERSHIPS - SEMAP / Campinas - SP, Brazil

Feb 2019 - Dec 2019

Prospected partnerships & negotiated with companies interested in talents within Applied Mathematics to raise funds for the annual week long event organized by SEMAP. The event's mission is to gather professionals to collaborate, discuss and share their experience with the latest technologies and researches in the field

MONITOR / TEACHER - Luiz Gonzaga Horta Lisboa State School / Campinas - SP, Brazil

Feb 2008 - Nov 2008

> Volunteered giving reinforcement classes in math and reading for underprivileged students between 10 to 12 years old. Also teached environmental awareness, elaborated recreational activities & served them lunch donated by our school's cafeteria.

INTERNSHIPS

SOFTWARE VALIDATION INTERN (full time) - Eldorado Research Institute / SP, Brazil

Oct 2015 - Jan 2016

➤ Validated impact of new **Android** updates in Motorola products. Began documenting **test & validation** processes to establish a procedure and created a drive centralizing all project information.

SOFTWARE TESTER INTERN (full time) - Phi Innovation / SP, Brazil

Mar 2015 - Set 2015

> Tested embedded Android and C based systems, Basic Android development and automated tests in Java.

C# DEVELOPER INTERN (full time) - CI&T / SP, Brazil

Jan 2014 - Dec 2014

- > 1st project TransCanada: C# .NET, MVC, SQL Server, Jira, Git, Scrum, code reviews and pair programming.
- > 2nd Project Makro: Kanban, Oracle PL/SQL, C# .NET, TFS with Git for versioning.